Guide to the William Styron Papers, 1855-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Styron papers 1855-2007
Styron, William
29.8 linear feet Extent: 24510 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American author and Duke University alumnus. The William Styron Papers span the years 1855-2007, with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1943 and 1996. The collection consists of correspondence; writings by Styron and other authors; printed materials (including serials containing articles by and about Styron and his work as well as newspaper and magazine clippings); audiotapes, videotapes, and photographs; legal and financial papers; speeches and addresses; interviews; scrapbooks; and other material relating to Styron's personal life and his career as a writer. Extensive personal and professional correspondence between his family, friends, and fellow authors provides insight into his education at Duke University (particularly his studies with Professor William Blackburn of the Department of English) as well as his literary career and personal life.
RL.01267
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restrictions apply to some parts of the William Styron Papers.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The main body of the papers of William Styron was acquired from William Styron between 1969 and 1997. Small portions of the collection were donated by others or purchased between 1970 and 2008. All of Accession 2008-0072 and parts of Accession 2008-0294 remain on deposit.
Biographical Note
1925, June 11 Born to William Clark Styron and Pauline (Abraham) Styron, in Newport News, Va.
1942 Attended Davidson College
1943 Enlisted in Marine Corps in V-12 program Transferred to Duke University
1944-1945 Served as lieutenant in the Marine Corps
1947 Received A.B. from Duke University Moved to New York City and studied writing with Hiram Haydn at the New School for Social Research Associate editor with McGraw-Hill Book Company, New York, N.Y.
1952 Received American Academy of Arts and Letters Prix de Rome for Lie Down in Darkness (1951)
1953, May 4 Married Rose Burgunder
1960 Published the novel, Set this House on Fire
1968 Received Pulitzer Prize for The Confessions of Nat Turner (1967)
1970 Received Howells Medal of the American Academy of Arts and Letters for The Confessions of Nat Turner
1979 Publication of Sophie's Choice
1980 Received the American Book Award and nominated for the National Book Critics Circle Award, both for Sophie's Choice
1984 Received Connecticut Arts Award and Duke University's Distinguished Alumni Award Appointed a fellow of Silliman College of Yale University
1985 Received the Prix Mondial del Duca
1987 Received the Commandeur de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres
1988 Received Edward MacDowell Medal
1990 Publication of Darkness Visible: A Memoir of Madness, a narrative recalling the major depression Styron suffered beginning in 1985
2006 November Died at the age of 81 in Martha's Vineyard
Collection Overview
The William Styron Papers span the years 1855-2007 with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1943 and 1996. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Writings by Styron (which includes Separate Publications, Contributions to Books and Periodicals, Speeches, Unfinished Work, and Miscellaneous Writings), Writings by Others, Printed Material, Audiovisual Material, Scrapbooks, and Miscellaneous Material. Extensive personal and professional correspondence between Styron and his family, friends, editors, and fellow authors provides insight into his education at Duke University (particularly his studies with Professor William Blackburn of the Department of English) as well as his literary career and personal life. The Writings by Styron Series includes numerous drafts, notes, manuscripts, and proofs of his novels, essays, speeches, and articles. Critical and analytical works concerning Styron's writing can be found in both the Printed Material Series and the Writings by Others Series. Interviews with Styron are to be found in both the Interviews section of the Writings by Others Series and in the Audiovisual Material Series.
Numerous American authors are represented in the collection in the Correspondence Series as well as in the Writings by Others Series. Among the major correspondents are Robert Penn Warren, Carlos Fuentes, Norman Mailer, and Reynolds Price. Letters from Eudora Welty, Truman Capote, Art Buchwald, Richard Wilbur, Kurt Vonnegut, William Kennedy, and James Dickey are also included. A separate index to some of the letters by well-known authors and celebrities accompanies the collection. The Writings by Others Series also includes limited edition copies of poems by Reynolds Price and Allen Tate.
Styron's close relationship with his family is documented in the early letters of the Correspondence Series as well as in the scrapbooks kept by his father. The latter include much juvenilia and childhood memorabilia as well as clippings documenting his early literary accomplishments. A diary kept by Styron during the year following his mother's death appears in the Writings by Styron Series: Miscellaneous Writings Subseries. The Audiovisual Material Series includes several family photographs. Videotapes in this series also provide much information about his life and work.
Among the Writings by Styron are numerous holograph notes, manuscripts written in pencil, and printed texts and typescripts with revisions. These provide detailed insight into Styron's creative process and enable the researcher to document the evolution of much of Styron's work. Research material used by Styron for some of his work, particularly The Confessions of Nat Turner, appears among the volumes in the Printed Material Series.
Styron's experience with having his work filmed for both television and the cinema is documented by screenplays of The Long March and Sophie's Choice. Several photographs of the latter production appear in the Audiovisual Material Series. A screenplay of Set This House on Fire, a first draft of a screenplay of Lie Down in Darkness, and a step outline of The Confessions of Nat Turner, none of which were produced, also appear in the Writings by Others Series
Unprocessed addition (06-105) (0.4 lin. ft) contains Styron's copy of The Confessions of Nat Turner and a binder of letters from Styron to Bertha Krantz, Robert D. Loomis, and others, 1967-1993.
Unprocessed addition (07-145) (6 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 2007) contains copies of material from Styron's memorial service, including the program, book of reminiscences, and transcript. This material is boxed in box 1 of 08-142.
Unprocessed addition (08-012) (0.8 lin. ft.; 600 items; dated 1943-2006 and undated) includes published and unpublished essays, drafts, speeches, and writings by Styron, as well as copies of letters to his father (1943-1952) and correspondence from his wife, Rose, from around the time of his death in 2006. Also includes a leather portfolio with drafts of his work, photographs, clippings, and a photograph album from his daughter's film, Shadrach.
Unprocessed addition (08-072) (180 items, .6 lin. ft.; dated 1990-2003 and undated) comprises mainly letters to Styron regarding his works, especially DARKNESS VISIBLE. Also includes letters regarding appearances requested or planned.
Unprocessed addition (08-142) (388 items, .8 lin. ft; dated 1966-2007 and undated) mainly comprises incoming correspondence, which occasionally contains clippings, photographs, and other incidental materials. In addition, includes original manuscripts for several short works by the author, many annotated, as well as some handwritten manuscript pages for SOPHIE'S CHOICE. There are also two dvds of Styron's memorial service. Box 1 of this material includes Acc. 07-145.
Unprocessed addition (08-294) (0.4 lin. ft.; 300 items) was acquired and donated by James West III, and includes manuscripts, essays, edited drafts, and speeches by Styron. Each manuscript includes a cover page by West describing the condition of the materials. This material is boxed with Acc. 08/012.
Addition (11-142) (0.6 lin. ft.; 500 items) was donated by Styron's editor, Robert Loomis. It includes drafts and clippings, as well as photographs used in Styron publications.
Additions (12-017 and 12-131) (1.2 lin. ft.; 500 items) includes various writings and research.
Subject Headings
Styron, William, 1925-; Styron, William, 1925 -- Biography; Blackburn, William Maxwell, 1899-; Duke University. Dept. of English -- History; American literature -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-; Fuentes, Carlos; Mailer, Norman
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1914-1997 and undated
  The correspondence series is arranged chronologically and consists mostly of letters addressed to William Styron, but includes some written by him. Correspondents include family members, friends, teachers, publishers, and admirers of his work as well as other authors. A bound volume of letters to and from Donald Harrington is housed in box C 14 at the end of the chronologically arranged letters. Box C-15 contains restricted correspondence.
  - 1914-1953, (16 folders) (Box C 1)
  - 1954-1963, (10 folders) (Box C 2)
  - 1964-1967, (6 folders) (Box C 3)
  - 1968-1971, (6 folders) (Box C 4)
  - 1972-1977, (6 folders) (Box C 5)
  - 1978-1979,Aug., (5 folders) (Box C 6)
  - 1979, Sept.-1980, July, (5 folders) (Box C 7)
  - 1980, Aug.-1981, June, (5 folders) (Box C 8)
  - 1981, July-1983, (6 folders) (Box C 9)
  - 1984-1987, (8 folders) (Box C 10)
  - 1988-1989, (6 folders) (Box C 11)
  - 1990, (5 folders) (Box C 12)
  - 1991-1995, (9 folders) (Box C 13)
  - 1996-1997, undated, (7 folders) (Box C 14)
  - Correspondence with Donald Harrington (bound), 1960-1986, (1 folder)
  - Restricted Correspondence (Box C 15)
- Writings by Styron Series, 1941-1997 and undated
  Literary works by Styron are arranged in the following subseries: Separate Publications, Contributions to Books and Periodicals, Speeches, Unfinished Work, and Miscellaneous Writings.
  - Separate Publications Subseries, 1951-1993.
    Drafts, typescripts, proofs, editions, and fragments of Styron's published monographic works, including some with Styron's revisions. Arranged chronologically by date of publication.
    - Lie Down in Darkness,1951, 1979 (Box WS 1)
      - Versions of beginning chapters, (1 folder)
      - Advance galleys,1951, (1 folder)
      - Page proof,1979, (3 folders)
    - Set This House on Fire,1960 (Box WS 2)
      - Spiral bound galleys, (1 folder)
    - The Confessions of Nat Turner, 1967
      - Research file, (1 folder)
      - Advance galleys, (1 folder)
      - Japanese edition, (1 volume) (Box WS 3)
    - The Long March,1968
      - Carbon typescript, (1 folder)
      - Screenplay, (1 folder)
    - In the Clap Shack,1972
      - Fragments, (1 folder)
      - Holograph, (1 folder)
      - Manuscript, (1 folder)
      - Manuscript with holographic revisions, (1 folder)
      - Manuscript, (1 folder)
    - Dead: A Love Story, 1976 (Box WS 4)
      - Manuscript, (1 folder)
      - Typescript of screenplay, (1 folder)
    - Message of Auschwitz, 1979,printer's proof, (1 folder) (Box WS 5)
    - Sophie's Choice, 1979
      - Original holograph, (6 folders)
      - Rejected manuscript pages, (1 folder)
      - Setting copy, (6 folders) (Box WS 6)
      - Master set, 1st pass, (3 folders) (Box WS 7)
      - Master set, 2nd pass, (3 folders)
      - Page proof, (2 folders) (Box WS 8)
      - Galley, (3 folders)
      - Miscellaneous holograph fragments, (1 folder)
      - Author's corrected galleys (1 bosed item) (Box WS 9)
    - This Quiet Dust, 1982 (Box WS 10)
      - Corrections, (1 folder)
      - Setting copy, (2 folders)
      - Proof, (2 folders)
      - Galley proof, (2 folders) (Box WS 11)
      - Introduction and 4 new holograph essays, (1 folder)
    - Darkness Visible, 1990 (Box WS 12)
      - Galleys for Vanity Fair version, (1 folder)
      - Book jackets, (1 folder)
      - Early holograph fragments, (1 folder)
      - Incomplete holograph, (1 folder)
      - Final manuscript, (1 folder)
      - Page proof, (2 folders)
      - Proof, (1 folder)
      - Author's galleys, (1 folder)
      - Typescript with revisions, (1 folder)
    - A Tidewater Morning, 1994 (Box WS 13)
      - Front material, book jackets, (1 folder)
      - A Tidewater Morning, galley,1987, (1 folder)
      - "Shadrach," manuscript and typescript, n.d (1 folder)
      - Setting manuscript, (1 folder)
      - Die copy, (1 folder)
      - Master set, 1st pass, (1 folder)
      - Master set, 2nd pass, (1 folder)
      - Proof, (1 folder)
      - Page proof, (1 folder)
  - Contributions to Books and Periodicals Subseries, 1944-1996 and undated
    Typescripts, manuscripts, and photocopies of Styron's contributions to books and periodicals are divided into the following sections: Short Stories, Essays and Articles, and Introductions and Contributions to the Works of Others. Within each section, the material is arranged chronologically by date of publication.
    - Short Stories (Box WS 14)
      - 1944, Jan., The Archive - "Where the Spirit Is", (1 folder)
      - 1944, Mar., The Archive - "The Long Dark Road", (1 folder)
      - 1944, Sept., The Archive - "Sun on the River", (1 folder)
      - 1944, Dec., The Archive - "A Story About Christmas", (1 folder)
      - 1945, Feb., The Archive - "Autumn,", (1 folder)
      - 1946, May, The Archive - "This is My Daughter", (1 folder)
      - 1946, Oct., The Archive - "The Ducks" (1 folder
      - 1965, April, Harper's Magazine - "This Quiet Dust", (1 folder)
      - 1978, Mar. 14, Esquire - "My Life as a Publisher", (1 folder)
      - 1985, May 7, Esquire - "Love Day", (1 folder)
      - 1995, Sept. 18, New Yorker - "A Victim of the Great Pox", (1 folder)
      - 1996, April, Paris Review - "Transcontinental with Tex", (1 folder)
    - Essays and Articles
      - 1946, Sept., The Archive - Review of An Almanac for Moderns by Daniel C. Peattie, (1 folder)
      - 1946, Oct., The Archive - Essay on Dr. Newman Ivy White (1 folder
      - 1946, Dec., The Archive - Essay on Dr. Joseph Banks Rhine, (1 folder)
      - 1961, in The Artists' and Writers' Cookbook - "Southern Fried Chicken", (1 folder)
      - 1965, June, Harper's Magazine - Letter to Harper's Magazine, (1 folder)
      - 1969, Spring, in The Southern Literary Journal - "The Use of History in Fiction", (1 folder)
      - 1972, Summer, American Scholar - Review of The Aonheiter Affair, by Neil Sheehan, (1 folder)
      - 1972, June, New York Times Book Review - Review of Lt. Calley, by John Sack and The Court-Martial of Lt Calley, by Richard Hammer, (1 folder)
      - 1972, Mar., The Washington Monthly - Review of 365 Days, by Ronald J. Glasser, (1 folder)
      - 1973, May6, New York Times Book Review - Review of A Second Flowering, by M. Cowley, (1 folder)
      - 1974, June, New York Times - Op-ed page, (1 folder)
      - 1976, Dec. 19, Washington Post - "Potomac", (1 folder)
      - 1981, NY Review of Books - Review of The Civil War, by Mary Chestnut, (1 folder)
      - 1982, Jan., The Hartford Courant - Account of writing Lie Down in Darkness, (1 folder)
      - 1983, May, Le Figaro - Essay on influence of cinema on his writing
      - 1983, Dec., Esquire - "The Harbor: Edgartown, MA, Aug.1963"
      - 1984, Fall, Architectural Digest - Essay on Thomas Wolfe's house, (1 folder)
      - 1985, Aug., Esquire - "Love Day,", (1 folder)
      - 1987, May 10,New York Times - "Death Row", (1 folder)
      - 1987, June, Esquire - Essay on Virginia Foster Durr, (1 folder)
      - ca. 1987, Observer and New York Times Book Review Essay on James Baldwin, (2 folders)
      - 1988, Dec. 21, New York Times - Op-ed piece on Primo Levi, (1 folder)
      - 1989, Aug., Vanity Fair - Essay on Irwin Shaw, (1 folder)
      - 1989, Dec., Vanity Fair - "From the Abyss: Reflections of My Mind's Disorder", (2 folders)
      - 1991, April4, Time - "A Father's Prophecy", (1 folder)
      - 1991, June 16, New York Times Book Review - Review of Fortunate Son, by Lewis B. Puller, Jr., (1 folder) (Box WS 15)
      - 1991, Oct., Vineyard Gazette - Review of Deadline, by James Reston, (1 folder)
      - 1992, American Heritage, Oct. - "Nat Turner Revisited"
      - 1992, Time - Essay on the family, (2 folders)
      - 1993, Jan.4, Newsweek - Article on Hiroshima and Auschwitz, (1 folder)
      - 1993, Sept., Newsweek - Essay on depression, (1 folder)
      - 1993, The Nation [v. 256, n. 1] - "Prozac Days, Halcion Nights", (1 folder)
      - 1994, Summer, Audubon Magazine - Response to proposed Disney theme park in Virginia, (1 folder)
      - 1994, Dec., American Heritage - Comment, (1 folder)
      - 1995, Apr. 23, New York Times - Letter
      - 1995, June, The New Yorker - Essay on Mark Twain, (1 folder)
      - 1995, Aug., The New Yorker - Essay on Lolita, (1 folder)
      - 1995, Oct.8, New York Times Book Review - "A Childhood Transgression", (1 folder)
      - 1996, Jan., Le Monde - Essay on the death of Mitterand
      - 1996, Cigar Aficionado - Essay on JFK and cigars, (1 folder)
      - 1996, Egoiste - Essay on Terazosin, (1 folder)
      - Undated, High Fidelity - Review of JFK: As We Remember Him, (1 folder)
      - Undated, New York Times Book Review - Review of The Joint, by James Blake, (1 folder)
      - Undated, New York Times Book Review - Review of Reminiscences, by Douglas MacArthur, (1 folder)
      - Undated, London Observer - Essay on James Baldwin, (1 folder)
    - Introductions and Contributions to Works of Others
      - 1975, May - Preface for a bibliography by James L.W. West III, (1 folder)
      - 1982, Jan.- Introduction for the Franklin Mint edition of The Confessions of Nat Turner, (1 folder)
      - 1982, Feb.- Introduction for the French edition of Whistler, by James Jones, (1 folder)
      - 1982, April- Introduction for The Wheat and the Chaff, by Francois Mitterand, (1 folder)
      - 1983, June- Introduction for The Cunning of History, by Richard Rubenstein, (1 folder)
      - 1988 - Introduction for US-Soviet collaborative prose and poetry collection, (1 folder)
      - 1988, Sept.- Afterward to Bernard Faber article, published in Esquire, (1 folder)
      - 1988 - Preface for The View from Space, (1 folder)
      - 1989 - Introduction for Letters of James Jones, (1 folder)
      - 1990 - Introduction to Doing Justice, (1 folder)
      - 1993 - Introduction for The Face of Mercy, (1 folder)
      - 1995 - Introduction to Convicting the Innocent, (1 folder)
      - 1996 - Introduction for Dog Eat Dog, by Edward Bunkin, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for A Death in Canaan, by Joan Barthel, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for Paris Review volume of interviews, 9th series, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for Inheritance of Night, by William Styron, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for The Human Experience, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for Writers at Work, Vol. 9, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for No Beast So Fierce, by Edward Bunker, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for Fathers and Daughters, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Introduction for portfolio of etchings by Harold Altman, (1 folder)
      - Undated - Essay for Betsy Locke's book on Duke alumni, (1 folder)
      - Undated - "On Hellman, for book by Roddy McDowell, (1 folder)
  - Speeches Subseries, 1942-1996 and undated
    Transcripts of speeches written and mostly presented by Styron at commencements, memorial services, conferences, and award ceremonies, and upon other occasions. Arranged chronologically by date of presentation.
    - 1942 - Commencement address at Christchurch School, (1 folder) (Box WS 16)
    - 1973, May- Commencement address at Christopher Newport College, (1 folder)
    - 1975, April 4 - "Admiral Robert Penn Warren and the Snows of Winter," New York City Lotus Club, (1 folder)
    - 1975, April 10- Tribute to Robert Penn Warren, (1 folder)
    - 1975, May- Speech on Howells Medal, (1 folder)
    - 1975 - Commencement address at Christchurch School, (1 folder)
    - 1980, May- "Almost A Rhodes Scholar: A Personal Reminiscence", (1 folder)
    - 1980 - Commencement address at Hampden-Sydney College, (1 folder)
    - 1981, May 11- Commencement address at Duke University, (2 folders)
    - 1982, April 26- "Virginian of the Year" acceptance speech, (1 folder)
    - 1982, April 27- Address at Carnegie Hall, (1 folder)
    - 1983, January- Speech at NY Film Critics Award ceremony, (1 folder)
    - 1983, May 28- Commencement address at Taft School, (1 folder)
    - 1983 - "Mr. Jefferson and Our Times," Convocation address at University of Virginia, (1 folder)
    - 1984, Sept. 25- Truman Capote memorial, (1 folder)
    - 1984, Oct. 27- Connecticut Arts Award acceptance speech, (1 folder)
    - 1984, Nov. 18- Remarks at Paul Green/Lone Vigil convocation at Duke University, (1 folder)
    - 1987, Oct. 30- Remarks for panel at Duke University, (1 folder)
    - 1987, Nov. 30- Acceptance for Legion of Honor, (1 folder)
    - 1988, May 15- Commencement address at Claremount-McKenna College, (1 folder)
    - 1988, July- 85th birthday speech for Virginia Foster Durr, (1 folder)
    - 1989, April 7- Address to Fellowship of Southern Writers, (1 folder)
    - 1989, May 4 - Address on depression, (1 folder)
    - 1989, Nov. 9 - Speech at Bobst Award ceremony, (1 folder)
    - 1990, May 30- Graduation speech at American University in Paris, (1 folder)
    - 1990, May- Presenting the Howells Medal Award Citation to E.L. Doctorow, (1 folder)
    - 1990, Oct.- Tribute to Arthur Miller, (1 folder)
    - 1991, Jan.- Speech for McDowell Colony fund-raiser, (1 folder)
    - 1991, Jan.- Funeral tribute to Bernard Faber, (1 folder)
    - 1991, Feb. 28- Tribute to Philip Roth at National Arts Club, (1 folder)
    - 1991, Nov. 23- "Some Reflections on Europe and America," presented to European Parliament, (1 folder)
    - 1991, Dec. 5 - Convocation remarks at Duke University's Founders' Day, (1 folder)
    - 1992, Feb.- Statement on Salmon Rushdie, (1 folder)
    - 1993, Jan. 14- City Lights Society address, (1 folder)
    - 1993, March 28- Speech at Boston Public Library, (1 folder)
    - 1993, June 1- Remarks at ABA meeting in Miami, Fl., (1 folder)
    - 1995, May 4 - Statement at 40th anniversary party, (1 folder)
    - 1995, October- Remarks at Holocaust Museum, Washington, D.C., (1 folder)
    - 1995, Fall - Talk at Davidson College, (1 folder)
    - 1995, Nov. 9 - Talk on genesis of Sophie's Choice, (1 folder)
    - 1995, Nov. 29- Remarks, in absentia, at award for Tipper Gore, (1 folder)
    - 1996, May- Commencement address at Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, (1 folder)
    - 1996 - Acceptance speech for French Legion of Honor, (1 folder)
    - 1997, Jan.- Tribute to Robert Loomis, (1 folder)
    - Undated - Tribute to Philip Rahv; acceptance of Howells Medal, (1 folder)
    - Undated - Fragments of 2 speeches, (1 folder)
    - Abbie Hoffman, (1 folder)
  - Unfinished Work Subseries, 1970-1990s and undated
    Portions of 2 unfinished novels, unfinished works on Nicaragua and Carlos Fuentes, and an unfinished memoir about Styron's father. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1970-1985- The Way of the Warrior, (4 folders) (Box WS 17)